Today's
דף Daf is מ, Mem, but we start from the three lines,
a few lines from the bottom on ל"ט עמוד ב', Lamed Tet
Amud Bet,
and we pick up with the following. So we're on ל"ט עמוד
ב', Lamed Tet Amud Bet,
and the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Let's take a look.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. I'm sorry, just looking
for the exact place,
because if רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, it is six lines before the
line get wide, eight lines before the bottom of the page. If
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, what?
Okay. So it's on ל"ט עמוד ב', Lamed Tet Amud Bet, רב
נחמן. Rav Nachman. So here we go.
So the discussion
was whether garments, garments not of wool and linen are חייב chayav
in ציצית. tzitzit. So let's take a look. רב נחמן Rav Nachman
and רב נחמן Rav Nachman to the תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Tana
Debei Rabbi Yishmael goes like this. דבי רבי ישמעאל, Debei Rabbi Yishmael,
תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana Debei Rabbi Yishmael, we taught in the
house of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, כל שנאמרו בתורה סתם, kol shenemru
baTorah stam, ציצית tzitzit are generally just used with the
phrase בגד, beged, garment, without any explication, ופרט לך
הכתוב באחד מהן צמר ופשתים, u'ferat lecha hakatuv be'echad mehen tzemer u'pishtim,
and explicitly says by שעטנז, shatnez, לא תלבש שעטנז צמר ופשתים יחדיו.
lo tilbash shatnez tzemer u'pishtim yachdav. So it says it explicitly and
also by נגעים negaim it says בגד צמר או בגד פשתים, beged
tzemer o beged pishtim, which is more probably what the גמרא Gemara
means, which is a garment of wool or a garment of linen.
So it says explicitly that garment refers to wool or linen. So
therefore אף כל צמר ופשתים. af kol tzemer u'pishtim. Whenever it says
garment, it means specifically wool or linen and therefore that's his position
that the other types of garments are not obligated from the תורה
Torah in ציצית. tzitzit. So cotton and silk and so on would
only be a rabbinic obligation. אביי Abaye says, והאי תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל מהפך מהאידך תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. ve'hai Tana Debei Rabbi Yishmael
mehapech me'idach Tana Debei Rabbi Yishmael. The following teachings from the house
of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael actually reject the earlier teaching, so there's
contradictory teachings from the house of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. What are
these teachings? תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana Debei Rabbi Yishmael, we have
taught in the house of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, בגד, beged, אין
לי אלא בגד צמר. ein li ella beged tzemer. It says, the
תורה Torah says, רש"י Rashi says this is when the תורה Torah
is talking
about
נגעים. negaim. תוספות Tosafot says that it's not based on the word
used, it's actually talking about the things that become טמא tamei when
a שרץ sheretz touches it, when a dead bug touches it. But
either way, all I know is
בגד. beged. אין לי אלא בגד צמר. ein li ella beged tzemer.
I only know a classic type of בגד, beged, meaning one made
out of wool. מניין לרבות צמר גמלים וצמר ארנבים, minayin lerabot tzemer
gemalim ve'tzemer arnavim, how do I know it can include the hair
of camels and the wool of rabbits, a rabbit wool, ונוצה של
עזים, ve'notza shel izim, and the hair
of
goats, והכלך והסריקין והשיראים, ve'hakalach ve'haserikin ve'hashira'im, different types of silk? How
do I know all of these things are included in the word
בגד beged for this issue of טומאה? tumah? And the answer is
מניין, minayin, תלמוד לומר או בגד. talmud lomar o beged. The או,
o, which is more inclusive, comes to interpret mean even non-standard בגדים,
begadim, even non-traditional
material. תוספות Tosafot asks that it's hard to know from either of
these which is the general rule because here you have the word
או בגד o beged including a wider range, and perhaps by ציצית
tzitzit you have the word כנף מין כנף kanaf min kanaf to
tell you all types of garments. So it's hard to know what
the general rule is and it's a little curious that the גמרא
Gemara seems she can ask the question from נגעים negaim or from
שרצים shratzim to the issue of ציצית. tzitzit. But regardless, there remains
to be a general question, which is when the תורה Torah refers
to clothes, does it refer to only wool or linen or all
types? And specifically by ציצית, tzitzit, are other types of garments, are
they דאורייתא de'oraita or rabbinic in terms of the obligation? The reason
that this is really relevant to us is
because we, if you just happen to be wearing a four-cornered garment,
so who cares, either way you're חייב chayav in ציצית tzitzit and
you make a ברכה bracha as long as it's rabbinically obligated. The
reason it's relevant is because as we said the other day,
our practice
is
not just to wait until you're wearing a four-cornered garment, our practice
is to go out of the way to wear a four-cornered garment
so that we're obligated in
ציצית. tzitzit. And therefore, if we're trying specifically so hard to do
the מצווה, mitzvah, presumably we would, all things being equal, we'd like
to do the מצווה דאורייתא mitzvah de'oraita rather than just doing the
rabbinic מצווה. mitzvah. So we're going to try to wear the type
of garment that's biblically obligated. So the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch paskens
according to the opinion in the גמרא Gemara here that like we
just said
about
רב נחמן Rav Nachman that only wool and linen. The רמ"א Rama
paskens the other opinion that all garments are חייב chayav in ציצית
tzitzit and all are biblical. And I wrote about this in my
blog the other day, the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah says, you know,
if you want to be ירא שמים, yerei shamayim, so you're not
going to just rely on this debate and you'll try to make
sure you're being יוצא yotzei the מצווה mitzvah and you'll wear wool
ציצית, tzitzit, which is why we do that. Why people have the
מנהג. Minhag. Some people have the מנהג, Minhag, not everybody of course,
but some people have the מנהג Minhag like myself to always wear
wool ציצית Tzitzit and even your even your טלית קטן, Tallit Katan,
your undergarments. The problem is that that can be a חומרא Chumra
that leads to a קולא Kula because when it comes the summer
months, that can be very,
you know, that can be very uncomfortable,
and therefore some people will say forget it, I'm not even wearing
the ציצית Tzitzit at all unless you're really פרום Frum then you
enjoy the fact that you're suffering when you're doing the מצוה. Mitzvah.
So anyway, certainly if that's an issue a person should wear cotton
ציצית Tzitzit at least during the summer month because rather than wear
decide you're going to wear wool ציצית Tzitzit and then not wear
any. And the אשכנזים Ashkenazim rule that that's even a דאורייתא De'oraita
and everybody agrees it's at least a דרבנן Derabbanan and you can
make a ברכה. Beracha. The real bigger question is the issue about
synthetic materials and I discussed that yesterday and in the posting of
the blog. So that's the issue in terms of wool and linen
versus other garments and now we are going to turn to the
official דף Daf of today מ״א ע״א Mem Amud Aleph and look
at really focus on the issue of שעטנז Shatnez and כלאים. Kilayim.
Alright, so here we are, unless any questions, we look now at
the top of מ״א ע״א. Mem Amud Aleph. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
our Rabbis taught. You can see how thick the תוספות Tosefot thing
here on this are on this דף. Daf. There's also the סוגיא
Sugya that appeared in parallel in the גמרא Gemara in שבת Shabbat
and you know, I don't know if you'll get a sense when
reading it, I got a sense that it's somehow a more tightly
constructed סוגיא, Sugya, it seems to be like a very compact סוגיא
Sugya with a lot packed in. So let's take a look. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught. Oh, there's a question. Who has
a question? דוב, Dov, you have a question?
I had a question.
Go ahead. Just yell in, I can hear you. You're on the
phone. What's your
question
דוב? Dov?
Fact I mentioned that, I said that תוספות Tosefot raises that question.
Why the גמרא Gemara assumes certain things are rules, you know, by
ציצית Tzitzit we have one פסוק Pasuk that says, you know, על
הכנף, Al Hakanaf, מין כנף, Min Kanaf, which the גמרא Gemara might
be read to include other types of garments. By טומאה Tumah here
we have the word בגד, Beged, which is more inclusive. So it's
not a little unclear how the גמרא Gemara compares them and why
it assumes that these are rules rather than each case maybe is
an exception or you know is telling you the special דין Din
and it's hard to know the rule. So תוספות Tosefot really does
not have a good answer to that, but yes, that is a
question that תוספות Tosefot asks.
Okay?
Alright, so let's now go on. Let's look at the top of
מ״א ע״א. Mem Amud Aleph. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. סדין בציצית. Sadin
Bitzitzit. So what's the story if you are wear if you're the
famous סדין בציצית? Sadin Bitzitzit? You are wearing your you have your
linen garment in your ציצית. Tzitzit. I keep on trying to adjust
this camera to get me more centered and it keeps on refusing
to do it. Maybe I'm moving it in the wrong way. Alright,
whatever. I know you don't need me exactly centered in the screen.
Whatever. Okay. סדין בציצית. Sadin Bitzitzit. בית שמאי פוטרין ובית הלל מחייבין.
Beit Shammai potrin u'Beit Hillel mechayvin. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you're
exempt from ציצית Tzitzit and בית הלל Beit Hillel says you're obligated.
Now, the question here is as רש״י Rashi points out, if you're
exempt from ציצית Tzitzit in a linen garment and you go ahead
and put them anyway, then you're going to have שעטנז. Shatnez. And
בית שמאי Beit Shammai could have just said that if you choose
to put your wool strings, again that's your תכלת, Techelet, your wool
strings, then you're going to be wearing שעטנז Shatnez and could have
said בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you transgress. But nevertheless the context
of the question is whether you're חייב בציצית Chayav Bitzitzit or not
with the consequence being if you're not חייב Chayav and you go
ahead and put ציצית Tzitzit on, it's going to be שעטנז Shatnez
and you will transgress. Now, why does בית שמאי Beit Shammai say
you're exempt? Oh wait, let me ask even a previous question. What
does it mean that there's a problem here because the garment is
linen and you want to do ציצית? Tzitzit? Yes, we know that
the תכלת Techelet has to be of wool, but the other strings
do not necessarily have to be of wool. So why does בית
שמאי Beit Shammai say you're exempt? Why didn't בית שמאי Beit Shammai
just say that you are that you go ahead and wear the
white strings without the blue strings? So it seems the simple read
of this, assuming we're talking at a biblical level, we'll talk at
a rabbinic level in a minute, is that they understand like רבי
Rebbi or like against our משנה, Mishnah, that the blue is מעכב
Me'akev the white. And since you need both the blue and the
white, if you can't do the blue, you can't do the white,
so you're totally exempt from ציצית. Tzitzit. And if you were to
put ציצית Tzitzit on and put wool strings on here, then it
would be שעטנז Shatnez and you would transgress. Now, why does בית
שמאי Beit Shammai say you're exempt? We just finished yesterday saying that
the whole תורה Torah
juxtaposes שעטנז Shatnez with ציצית Tzitzit to tell you that you can
wear שעטנז Shatnez with your ציצית, Tzitzit, especially here what you don't
have a choice where the garment is linen and your blue strings
have to be wool. So רש״י Rashi has two explanations. One is,
you know what, בית שמאי Beit Shammai does not buy into that
whole דרשה. Drasha. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says that
no, the תורה Torah is by juxtaposing it is not telling you
you're allowed to wear שעטנז Shatnez in your ציצית Tzitzit and in
this type of a garment you're exempt. Whatever happened to עשה דוחה
לא תעשה, Aseh docheh lo ta'aseh, a positive overrides a negative? Not
clear. But one thing רש״י Rashi says is בית שמאי Beit Shammai
does not buy into this whole idea that you're allowed
ציצית Tzitzit overrides wearing שעטנז. Shatnes. The other bit of רש״י Rashi
which makes a little more sense in the continuation of the גמרא
Gemara is that בית שמאי Beis Shammai is only talking rabbinically. Biblically
בית שמאי Beis Shammai admits that you're חייב chayiv in ציצית, tzitzis,
but he's afraid if you let people wear שעטנז shatnes in their
ציצית, tzitzis, then they're going to come and wear שעטנז shatnes even
when they're not let's say doing the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית. tzitzis.
Let's say if their blue is invalid as we're going to see
in the גמרא, Gemara, or other types of things, it'll lead to
שעטנז shatnes cases when you're not doing the מצוה, mitzvah, so they'd
rather say just don't do it at all and it's rabbinic, which
makes sense now. It answers a couple of things. It answers why
בית שמאי Beis Shammai does not say you transgress, because you don't
actually transgress שעטנז, shatnes, it's only a rabbinic thing to exempt you.
And it makes sense that בית שמאי Beis Shammai in principle does
buy into the idea that שעטנז shatnes is allowed in ציצית, tzitzis,
but he nevertheless is sort of afraid of it and therefore concerned
about it and therefore says don't do it at all. It fits
in in general to בית שמאי Beis Shammai's approach, which is to
be more you know make more safeguards. So the better way probably
to read בית שמאי Beis Shammai is the other way of רש״י,
Rashi, which is that this is a rabbinic safeguard. And of course
בית הלל מחייב, Beis Hillel mechayev, and בית הלל Beis Hillel says
no, forget all that. Even though you're going to have שעטנז shatnes
and it's wool strings in a linen garment, you're still חייב chayiv
in ציצית tzitzis and I'm not going to be afraid of it
might be to a שעטנז shatnes problem you know like you might
do it incorrectly. The תורה Torah allows you to do it and
you're חייב. chayiv. So let's read it that way that it's a
debate of whether there is a rabbinic prohibition or not. I should
also add that
רש״י Rashi
asks the question, well it's very nice that בית שמאי Beis Shammai
has these concerns that you might transgress, but if they're telling you
don't put ציצית tzitzis in this garment, then I'm going to be
walking around with a four-cornered garment without ציצית tzitzis in it. Because
remember again they're not just saying don't put the blue string. They're
saying don't put ציצית tzitzis at all, because they're afraid that if
they tell me to put ציצית tzitzis you know what will it
lead to? It'll lead to maybe שעטנז shatnes problems. So what about
the fact that I'm wearing a four-cornered garment without ציצית? tzitzis? And
רש״י Rashi says yes, this is one of the powers that the
rabbis have to tell you because of their concerns to passively not
do certain מצוות, mitzvos, like we're very familiar with it of course
by blowing the שופר shofar on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah on שבת
Shabbos and taking the לולב lulav on סוכות Succos on שבת Shabbos
and sometimes even more serious cases. And the rabbis can actually tell
me not to... I just lost the audio, the conference call fell
out for a second.
Always problems. Okay, so the rabbis can actually tell me don't bother
doing the מצוה. mitzvah. Now here we would think it's a little
worse, here we would think that it would tend to be something
like you know a ביטול עשה, bitul asey, not just a שב
ואל תעשה, shev ve'al taaseh, but nevertheless as long as I'm being
passive, that's within the
rabbinic authority. So that's בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. So very interesting read
of בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. You know, they're so concerned that it'll
lead to a שעטנז shatnes problem that they tell me that they
tell me not to do a biblical מצוה mitzvah and to passively
not fulfill a biblical מצוה mitzvah because they're concerned that it might
lead to a negative to transgress a negative, which I think certainly
reflects the general more sort of מחמיר machmir concern safeguard approach of
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. So that's what בית שמאי Beis Shammai says.
בית הלל Beis Hillel is the opposite of all this. You go
put your wool strings in, you have שעטנז, shatnes, it's ציצית, tzitzis,
not a problem. Now the גמרא Gemara continues, והלכה כדברי בית הלל,
ve'halacha k'divrei Beis Hillel, and we rule like בית הלל. Beis Hillel.
Interesting it says it in the ברייתא Baraita itself, although normally we
take that for granted. אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק, Amar Rabbi Elazar
bar Rabbi Tzadok,
והלא כל המטיל תכלת בירושלים אינו אלא מן המתמיהין. v'lo kol hamatilah
techeilet b'Yerushalayim eino ela min hamitmitemin. Anybody who puts blue in a
blue string in their ציצית tzitzis in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, if you look
at the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet he adds the word תכלת בסדין.
techeilet b'sadin. They're תכלת techeilet in their סדין, sadin, which is their
classic linen garment. Anybody who wears blue in their linen garment in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you know, is lead to people lead like makes people
astounded in the sense of shock, that nobody would ever do this
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Even if we rule like בית הלל, Beis Hillel,
nobody would ever do it, presumably saying either questioning בית הלל Beis
Hillel or explaining בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, but basically saying it might
technically be permitted but in ירושלים Yerushalayim they don't do it. Whether
they're like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, they don't do it, they're afraid
that it'll lead to unacceptable שעטנז shatnes situations even though it is
technically permitted. אמר רבי אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi Amar Rabbi, so רבי
Rabbi says, אם כן למה אסרוה? im ken lama asruha? If it
really is technically permitted, let's say according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai,
even בית שמאי Beis Shammai admits that technically you're still obligated, why
did they forbid you to do this? So the גמרא Gemara says,
לפי שאין בקיאין. lefi she'ein bekiin. So this is... yeah, Yedidya says
why... I have absolutely no idea why ירושלים, Yerushalayim, although I will
say that the גמרא Gemara does sometimes identify
like a pious group of people living in ירושלים Yerushalayim like it
speaks by סוכות, Succos, it says that if I'm remembering it correctly
it speaks about how certain חסידים הראשונים chassidim harishonim I think it
says in ירושלים Yerushalayim would go around holding their לולב lulav and
אתרוג esrog with them the whole day. So I think there's some
understanding that there were very people that very pious in ירושלים Yerushalayim
that took extra stringencies. Now it's one thing to take extra ways
of being very מדקדק... medakdek... the מצוות, mitzvos, like to always have
your לולב lulav and אתרוג esrog with you is another thing to
actually lead to it being anxiety of transgression and not doing מצוות,
mitzvos, which is what we're talking about here. Plus yet it does
seem that there was some like pious circles in ירושלים Yerushalayim at
the time of the משנה, Mishna, at the time of the גמרא,
Gemara, which had these additional stringencies. And this was the norm. So
now רבי Rebbe says, so therefore why if why are they making
it forbidden if technically it's allowed and not only allowed a מצוה?
mitzvah? So it says מפני שאין בקיאין. Mipeinei she'ein biki'im. Because people
don't know the הלכה. halacha. What does that mean people don't know
the הלכה? halacha? So רש"י Rashi says, they don't know that שעטנז
shatnez is permissible by ציצית, tzitzis, and if they see you wearing
שעטנז shatnez in your ציצית, tzitzis, they're going to say oh look
at that, you can wear שעטנז shatnez in your you know you
can wear שעטנז, shatnez, so I'll wear שעטנז shatnez in my garment
too even if I'm not doing the מצוה. mitzvah. Maybe I'll put
fringes on my you know on my linen garment not relating to
ציצית, tzitzis, and maybe שעטנז shatnez will be allowed. So basically what
we might call a concern of מראית עין, Maris Ayin, people are
ignorant, they'll see you, they'll come and do the wrong thing, and
because of that concern that it will lead to transgression בית שמאי
Beis Shammai said don't wear ציצית tzitzis in such a garment at
all. Now the גמרא Gemara is not happy. So let's take a
look. And this גמרא, Gemara, although obviously it's a fascinating גמרא Gemara
in terms of issues about עשה דוחה לא תעשה, aseh doche lo
sa'aseh, positive overriding a negative, and about שעטנז shatnez and ציצית, tzitzis,
is also a fascinating and very important גמרא Gemara in terms of
where the rabbis feel it is necessary to make safeguards to protect
people from inadvertent transgression. And specifically when it's an issue about ignorance.
So let's take a look. So the answer people don't know the
הלכה halacha and it'll lead them to making mistakes. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר ליה רבא בר רב חנה לרבא.
Amar lei Rava bar Rav Chana l'Raba. So רבא בר רב חנה
Rava bar Rav Chana said to
רבא, Raba, ולירמו ביה עשרה. V'lirmubia asarah. Why don't you gather a
מנין, minyan, gather ten people like obviously not the הלכתי halachic idea
of a מנין, minyan, but make a public statement, gather ten people,
ונפקו לשוקא, v'nafku l'shuka, let them all go out into the marketplace,
get ten פרום frum people around, have them wear you know linen
garments, and have them put ציצית tzitzis on it and take your
ten פרום frum people and do a little march through the marketplace
wearing your ציצית, tzitzis, ומפרסמא למילתא, u'mefarsem l'milsa, and then
it'll publicize it. So you know, just start changing the facts on
the ground, get people to see people wearing it rather than giving
in to the ignorance of the people, you know you should challenge
people's ignorance and go ahead and wear it and do it in
a way that people won't think oh it's just one idiot, have
a lot of people do it and everybody will realize that the
הלכה halacha is different. So the גמרא Gemara says no, that won't
solve the problem. כל שכן דמתמהי עלייהו. Kol shekein d'metamhei alayhu.
Certainly people will be astounded, meaning that people say oh my God,
look at this these פרום frum people, they're wearing שעטנז, shatnez, the
ignorance is so ingrained that publicizing it will not lead to a
shifting of perception, publicizing it will just lead to people you know
sort of castigating or casting aspersions I should say on those that
are violating these norms that are wearing the שעטנז shatnez in the
ציצית. tzitzis. So the גמרא Gemara says you know, publicizing often does
not do the factor change ignorance. So גמרא Gemara says okay, but
how about really working at changing ignorance? So what should you do?
So the גמרא Gemara says ולדרוש בפירקא. V'lidrosh b'pirka. Why not start
giving שיעורים, shiurim, you know start expounding this in the public gatherings
of learning, and start teaching people and address their ignorance, rather than
giving in to their ignorance, you know teach them otherwise and therefore
teach them that by ציצית tzitzis שעטנז shatnez is allowed and it's
a special exception and from there move on. Now this is such
a beautiful גמרא Gemara because you know normally we are think we
you know we're normally inclined to think that with concerns like you
know of מראית עין, Maris Ayin, that there's always an idea that
you have to always worry about how people are you know people
what people perceive even if it's not the facts. And this גמרא
Gemara says if there's a real problem with ignorance work at addressing
that rather than giving in to
it. I should say that there's a very important תשובה teshuvah of
רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein about a question of מראית עין,
Maris Ayin, which is is there a מראית עין Maris Ayin concern
if somebody is going to do something that is completely הלכתי halachic
but people are not aware that it's הלכתית halachically permissible? Meaning classic
מראית עין Maris Ayin is that the ignorance is in the facts,
not in the law. What's a classic example of מראית עין Maris
Ayin is that I take some soy cheese and I melt it
over my hamburger and I eat it and everybody thinks I'm eating
a cheeseburger. Okay that is not an ignorance of the law, it's
an ignorance of the fact. People see something and they don't know
the fact and it looks like I'm eating a cheeseburger. But what
about a מראית עין Maris Ayin when it's ignorance of the law?
Let's say for example I'm going to go ahead and do something
that actually is הלכתי halachic permissible but people think is not. Trying
to give let's say a good example of this but
what would be a good example of this?
I don't know I'm not thinking of one right now. But anyway
our גמרא Gemara is a good example of this. Everybody knows that
you're wearing שעטנז shatnez in your ציצית, tzitzis, they were just ignorant
of the fact that that's permissible, there's an ignorance of the law.
So is that מראית עין maris ayin when it's an ignorance of
the law and not an ignorance of fact? And רב משה פיינשטיין
Rav Moshe Feinstein says no. מראית עין maris ayin is only if
they're ignorant about the facts because we can't assume that people know,
you know, that the cheese on your hamburger is soy cheese. There's
not an, there's, they're, people have to know all of the facts
of other people's lives. So there there's a concern of מראית עין.
maris ayin. But if it's a people's ignorance in the law, then
let them learn the הלכה. halacha. They'll see you and they'll think,
"Oh my God, this guy's wearing ציצית, tzitzis, שעטנז shatnez in his
ציצית." tzitzis. So you know what? Big deal. Let them, let their,
let their assumptions be challenged but the הלכה halacha is that yes,
שעטנז shatnez is permissible in the ציצית. tzitzis. So that I think,
that type of attitude that we shouldn't worry less when people's ignorance
stems from ignorance of the law is really at the heart of
this גמרא. Gemara. Now the גמרא Gemara does say that sometimes you
don't change that ignorance by just acting otherwise, sometimes there has to
be some education and conversation that goes with it, but nevertheless we're
not really prepared to give in to people's ignorance of the law,
we want people to know the הלכה, halacha, not be ignorant of
the הלכה. halacha. Okay, now
דב, Dov, you had a question about sectarianism about
Jerusalem? Yeah, I can hear
you.
I was just
wondering that, was it specifically because, some people, around being, sure, yeah,
some people, around some time, almost say some people, Jerusalem?
Oh I see, so the מהר"ם לובלין, Maharam Lublin, right, meaning, so
I mean the way I was explaining it is it's just it's
so ingrained that people will think, "Look at all these פרום frum
rabbis that they're violating," but you're saying that actually it'll make them
think that they're actually some type of a sect was your point?
Not just violators, but it's actually a non-halachic practice and right. Well
that's certainly possible, especially, you know, in the time of the גמרא,
Gemara, the idea that there might have been more sectarianism. But right,
so that's the point. And again, it's a very I think astute
גמרא Gemara in saying sometimes ignorance is so ingrained that rather than
people allowing their assumptions to be challenged, they just persist on reading
the facts differently. So even if they see a lot of פרום
frum people, you know, doing this, they'll just say, "Look at all
those violators," or the way you want to have it, "Look at
all those people that have this new sect of wearing שעטנז shatnez
in their ציצית." tzitzis. So again, it's a great גמרא Gemara in
how on the one hand how deeply ingrained ignorance can be, the
resistance to
re-assess your assumptions, and at the other hand, the unwillingness to give
in to that, and not say that's a good reason. Saying no,
we have to resist that. So let's keep on going because גמרא
Gemara says like this.
So גמרא Gemara says, "Okay, ולידרשוה בפירקא, v'lidrashuh b'pirka, let's, why not
educate them otherwise?" So גמרא Gemara says, "גזירה משום קלא אילן." gezeira
mishum kala ilan.
No, we're afraid of קלא אילן. kala ilan. קלא אילן kala ilan
referred to a type of an artificial dye, a non-תכלת techeiles dye
that looked just like תכלת. techeiles. And therefore here's the concern, says
גמרא. Gemara. "You're right, we're not going to give in to people's
ignorance. The only reason we don't want to allow שעטנז shatnez in
ציצית, tzitzis, your תכלת techeiles in your linen ציצית, tzitzis, is because
people sell a false תכלת." techeiles. Right, there was a big market
in artificial תכלת. techeiles. תכלת techeiles was expensive, קלא אילן kala ilan
was cheap, so people would sell, the גמרא Gemara talks about this,
people would sell קלא אילן kala ilan at the price of discounted
תכלת. techeiles. But nobody would know, they would be tricking people and
this was a whole market. So גמרא Gemara says is if you
let people wear תכלת techeiles in their linen garments, then a lot
of people are going to not be wearing תכלת techeiles but קלא
אילן kala ilan and therefore they're not really going to be יוצא
yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of תכלת. techeiles. And if they're not יוצא
yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of תכלת, techeiles, it's שעטנז shatnez where שעטנז
shatnez is not necessary. Because again, שעטנז shatnez is only allowed, the
primary idea is is that if you need the wool strings because
of the מצוה mitzvah of תכלת, techeiles, but if you're not doing
the מצוה mitzvah of תכלת techeiles because it's bogus תכלת, techeiles, then
you don't need the wool strings and therefore it is a שעטנז
shatnez problem. Now let's just read another line and I'll explain this
a little more. So it says, גמרא Gemara says, "Big deal, ולא
יהא אלא לבן. v'lo yehei ella lavan. So let it not be
תכלת, techeiles, let's say you are being duped and your תכלת techeiles
is really the קלא אילן, kala ilan, and it's just like it
was white strings, it's not like it's blue strings, but nevertheless, so
you have, you're still doing a מצוה mitzvah of ציצית, tzitzis, and
should not doing the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית tzitzis allow you to
overcome the שעטנז shatnez problem?" גמרא Gemara says, "No, כיון דאפשר במינה
לא. keivan d'efshar b'minah lo. Since it's possible to do it with
linen strings and you don't need wool strings if you're not doing
the מצוה mitzvah of תכלת, techeiles, so therefore you are not able,
it's not good, לריש לקיש, l'Reish Lakish, like ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
דאמר ריש לקיש, d'amar Reish Lakish, because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says,
כל מקום שאתה מוצא עשה ולא תעשה, kol makom she'atah motzei asei
v'lo ta'asei, whenever there's an עשה asei which comes up against a
negative prohibition and we know the הלכה halacha is that..." So the
עשה asei overrides the negative prohibition. So אם אתה יכול לקיים את
שניהם מוטב, im ata yachol lekayeim et shneihem mutav, if you can
sort of avoid the conflict, do your positive מצוה mitzvah without transgressing,
find a workaround, then good. That's what you have to do and
you're not allowed to override the negative. ואם לאו, v'im lav, but
if you can't and the only way to fulfill the positive is
by transgressing the negative, יבא עשה וידחה לא תעשה. yavo asei v'yidche
lo ta'asei. Let the עשה asei come and override the לא תעשה.
lo ta'asei. So what's the גמרא Gemara saying? On the face of
it, what the גמרא Gemara is saying is the following: The only
reason we allow שעטנז shatnez in ציצית tzitzit is because there's no
way around it. The מצוה עשה mitzvah asei of wearing ציצית tzitzit
overrides the negative prohibition of שעטנז, shatnez, so when the only way
to do it is by שעטנז shatnez because I need my blue
strings, my blue strings can only be wool, my garment is linen,
so there's no way around it, I've got to use wool and
linen together, then I'm allowed. But when there's other ways around
it, like I don't have blue because I have this bogus blue,
so I'm not doing blue anyway, so I might as well use
linen strings, I don't have to have שעטנז, shatnez, in that case
you are not allowed to have שעטנז shatnez in your ציצית. tzitzit.
Read this way, the גמרא Gemara is saying that the only allowance
for שעטנז shatnez in the ציצית tzitzit is when there's no alternative.
Now you might remember from yesterday that that is not what we
said yesterday. Yesterday we said that if you had a wool garment
you could have linen ציצית, tzitzit, not the blue, but for the
white. Okay, why? Because once you're making ציצית tzitzit we don't care
about שעטנז shatnez in the making of the ציצית. tzitzit. That it
was a total blanket allowance. So why here does the גמרא Gemara
make it sound like it's only when it's an unavoidable conflict? So
it could be that these גמרות Gemarot debate. It could be that
some גמרא Gemara assumed that whenever you're having ציצית tzitzit it leads
to a שעטנז shatnez issue, it's a non-issue, it's a blanket allowance,
and that this גמרא Gemara says no, it's only when it's unavoidable.
That's one way of reading it. Another way of reading it is
a little bit sharper. And if you take a look at תוספות,
Tosafot, this little תוספות Tosafot which says כיון דאפשר במינן, keivan d'efshar
beminan, because
you'll notice that the language of the גמרא Gemara is like it's
not appropriate. The גמרא's Gemara language is like well, since you could
use linen, you shouldn't be using wool, like what ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says. It doesn't say technically this is an application of ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish and it's you know you're not allowed to override
because there's an option. It sounds like you know you shouldn't be
doing it this way because there's another way. So almost like an
analogy. The same way ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says that we don't
have the principle of עשה דוחה לא תעשה asei docheh lo ta'asei
when there's a workaround, so since there's a workaround here too, you
know it's not appropriate to be wearing שעטנז. shatnez. And it sounds
more from the tone of the גמרא Gemara that it's an issue
of appropriateness rather than an actual violation. So if you take a
look here תוספות, Tosafot, כיון דאפשר במינן, keivan d'efshar beminan, here's what
תוספות Tosafot says: לאו דבמסקנא דחוטי פשתן פוטרים בשל צמר, lav d'bamaskana
dechutei pishtan potrim beshel tzemar,
you can even wear linen strings in a wool garment where there's
no need to do that and we nevertheless allow it even though
it's שעטנז. shatnez. היינו בהדי תכלת. hainu behadi techelet.
That's only when you're also wearing תכלת. techelet. דמיגו דתכלת פטרה בשל
פשתן לבן נמי
פטר. demigo d'techelet patra beshel pishtan lavan nami patar. So תוספות Tosafot
is saying like this, is that תכלת techelet is what gives you
the free pass. We know how do we know שעטנז shatnez is
allowed, what's the one case that שעטנז shatnez is clearly allowed by
ציצית? tzitzit? When you have your wool תכלת techelet in your linen
garment. There there's no workaround, there you have to have שעטנז, shatnez,
there clearly it's allowed. So what תוספות Tosafot is saying is when
the other גמרות Gemarot talk about getting a free pass for שעטנז,
shatnez, that's when your תכלת techelet is coming along for the ride.
תכלת techelet is what gives you the free pass. So if you
have a wool garment and you have wool תכלת, techelet, once you
have the presence of תכלת, techelet, you're allowed to have שעטנז. shatnez.
And therefore your white strings can be linen. But in our גמרא,
Gemara, the whole problem is that your strings were קלא אילן, kala
ilan, not תכלת. techelet. So once you don't have
תכלת, techelet, then you do not have a free pass. It has
to be based on the עשה דוחה לא תעשה asei docheh lo
ta'asei principles. And therefore, and therefore
it would be a violation of שעטנז. shatnez. And this tends to
be תוספות's Tosafot general approach, and this is important in the whole
פרק התכלת, Perek HaTechelet, about thinking about you know the different status
of ציצית tzitzit when you're wearing תכלת techelet and not wearing תכלת.
techelet. Is it just another dimension of the מצוה, mitzvah, another brownie
point, another מצוה, mitzvah, or is it something qualitatively different? And תוספות
Tosafot basically says when you have the full-blown ציצית, tzitzit, the white
and the blue, then that is a full ציצית, tzitzit, and then
that is so powerful that שעטנז shatnez concerns are totally set aside.
Even if you don't need שעטנז, shatnez, it doesn't matter. When you're
dealing with full ציצית, tzitzit, תוספות Tosafot says it's like הותרה, hutra,
right? Not like דחויה, duchuya, which is the phrase they often use,
but הותרה. hutra. And שעטנז shatnez is then there's no concept of
שעטנז shatnez when you're doing ציצית סוג א. tzitzit sug alef. When
you're doing the full form of ציצית, tzitzit, שעטנז shatnez is a
non-issue. Not doing the full form of ציצית, Tzitzit, like you only
have white, you know the גמרא, Gemara, you thought you had the
blue, but it wasn't really the blue, now שעטנז Shatnez is a
problem. Maybe we can allow it if there's no choice, that they
דוחה לא תעשה, Docheh Lo Ta'aseh, but fundamentally שעטנז Shatnez is a
problem. There's something very beautiful about that because you know in the
בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehunah, you had sometimes that you had שעטנז Shatnez
in the בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehunah, and that was also because of
the תכלת, Techeiles, you know the תכלת Techeiles interwoven with the, with
the linen. So the idea that somehow תכלת Techeiles represents either is
evocative of בגדי כהונה Bigdei Kehunah if you want to go that
way, or represents a type of a, type of a בגד Beged
that can be excluded from the problems of כלאים, Kilayim, and that
these ציצית Tzitzit are on a totally different level with תכלת. Techeiles.
That is something that תוספות Tosfos gets from this. There's another answer
תוספות Tosfos has about it being a rabbinic concern, not a biblical
concern, but I'm going to deal with this answer. So what have
we said now? We said why is it we don't want people
wearing wool strings in their wool תכלת Techeiles in their linen garments?
And the answer is because those wool תכלת Techeiles will not always
be תכלת, Techeiles, and as soon as it's not תכלת, Techeiles, you
have שעטנז, Shatnez, and שעטנז Shatnez without,
and since there's no need for שעטנז, Shatnez, therefore you are violating.
And as תוספות Tosfos says, because without the תכלת Techeiles there is
no free pass for שעטנז Shatnez in your ציצית. Tzitzit. Another read
of תוספות Tosfos is no, biblically it's still okay, and ציצית Tzitzit
are always fully exempt from שעטנז Shatnez concern, but nevertheless rabbinically we
don't like it when you had another option. But I'm going to
go with the first read of תוספות Tosfos that it's a rabbinic,
it's a biblical one, and that ציצית Tzitzit without, and that ציצית
Tzitzit without תכלת Techeiles is a שעטנז Shatnez problem. And that's why
we have an issue here. Was there a question there?
No? Okay, so let's keep on reading in the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, ולבדקי U-livdeke so the גמרא Gemara says if your whole
concern is about the blue, why not, why not do a check?
Why not send people around, rabbinic governmental inspectors, and have them go
ahead and do random checking on the blue, and test whether it's
the real, that it's being sold, whether it's the real blue or
not the real blue? Because the גמרא Gemara later will say that
there are tests that you can run in order to determine whether
it's the real תכלת Techeiles or not. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא גזירה משום טעימה. Ella gezeirah mishum ta'ama.
We're concerned about tasting. What does tasting mean? That if the way
you do the test sometimes is you taste a little bit of
it and you use it, anyway it's a phrase that's referring to
the running of the test. If you take a sample and you
run a test and then you pour it back into the main
vat of the blue, that invalidates the vat even though it was
actually כשר. Kosher. Once this test has been run on it, the
גמרא Gemara later will say that pouring it back in will invalidate
it. So we're worried about that גמרא Gemara when we get to
it. But nevertheless the גמרא Gemara is saying no, having it, having
inspectors do it won't solve the problem because it'll still lead to
invalid blues out there because they'll do a test and they'll spill
it back and they'll invalidate it and so on. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, לכתוב אדיסקי. Lichtov adiski. Why not write a proclamation,
you know, post notices that's going to say everybody should be aware
that, you know, that this stuff has to really be real תכלת
Techeiles and not קלא אילן Kala ilan and maybe here are the
ways that you test for it. So why not try to, this
is another explanation of let's just try to enforce the situation. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this,
רש"י Rashi says it also means post notices that says that don't
pour the dye back into the vat after you've tested it. So
people should know, both do the testing and inform people not to,
not to do it in a way that's going to ruin the
vat. Do the testing and don't pour the dye back. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אדיסקי ליקום וליסמוך. Adiski leikum u-lismoch. What, you think
we can rely on posted notices? You know, people are sloppy, they're
not going to pay attention to that.
So,
yeah,
so
what's again fascinating here is I think the sensitivity to human nature.
Meaning on the one hand the גמרא Gemara says we do not
want to tolerate ignorance. We're not going to give in to ignorance.
Now we will acknowledge that there are people that cheat out there,
that's something to be concerned about, and we're going to say, oh
well why not try to address that problem? And in the end
the answer is I think a realistic assessment that, you know, we
cannot necessarily police and control everybody's behavior. So we cannot rabbinically הלכה
halachically give in to ignorance and say we're going to, you know,
we're going to do what the הלכה halachah says, but if we
think that the only way to solve a problem is by actually
sending out a whole series of inspectors and posting notices, let's be
realistic that isn't going to do the job. The funny thing is
that the גמרא Gemara thought that the inspectors could do the job
were it not for the concern about pouring the mix back. Dov,
you had a question?
What?
I
thought the responsibility would have been on the people wearing the things
about the priests. Big big difference.
Well, I guess the problem was with that if people were getting
you into a dark alley and say, "Psst, buddy, you want to
buy some תכלת?" techelet? then most people would understand that that wasn't
real תכלת. techelet. The bigger problem was that ostensibly legitimate store owners
were selling תכלת techelet because either they were duped or, you know,
I think that was the problem. So it was the תכלת techelet
that was sold publicly that a certain percentage of that market was
invalid and that you could check the store owners. If people knew
they were buying off of the black market, the consumer not the
retailer, then you know, okay, you know what you're getting into. We
can't address that situation. So that's my sense is that we're not
doing it when the consumer knows they're buying black market, then you
know you get what's coming to you. We're talking about when the
consumer thinks they're buying something legitimate. So why don't the rabbis then
do something to run tests and to make sure? That seems to
be the assumption. But again, the assumption that the rabbis have a
whole police force out there that they can send inspectors, you know,
is pretty interesting. It reminds me of a case where this comes
up in כשרות, kashrut, you know, about the big question is: can
you buy fish that doesn't have the fins and scales on it,
what's it called, filleted fish, which is being, you know, the people
are telling you, like the store owner says, "You know, this is
whatever, this is cod, this is whitefish."
So, you know, kosher species. So salmon and tuna you can tell
just by looking at them, but how about the whitefishes? So for
a long time I was doubtful about that because how much do
we assume that people are going to be, you know, the argument
yes is nobody would mislead, it would lead to problems in their
business, you know, they'd get in trouble, so that would keep them
honest. But, you know, can you really rely on that? Anyway, about
five years ago, some two high school seniors, two girls, did a
science fair project where they bought fish at the local market and
then they ran DNA tests on it to see if the fish
was what it was claimed to be. And a very high percentage
was not. It was like lower-end fish being sold as higher-end fish,
and, you know, one species being claimed as another species. So after
that test was run, you know, I tell people that unless it's
tuna or salmon, which you can really just see by looking at
the flesh, that, you know, you can't buy fish unless you actually
see, you know, unless it's from a normal fish seller unless you
see the fins and scales or you see them filleted in front
of you. Anyway, so one of my students told me that, you
know, the question is: so what did the government respond to this?
And the government's response, you know, if I mean, aren't they supposed
to try to protect the consumer, you know, if there's all this
fake fish being sold that's not genuine out there? So the government
actually said the problem is so widespread that it would require so
much manpower to address it that they're not going to address it.
Which I thought was pretty hubris, I mean, you know, because how
much would it require to do a couple of spot inspections? But
anyway, it's very similar to here. The US government can't address the
problem of fish being mislabeled and we think that we're going to
send some consumer, you know, some rabbinic task force out there to
address the problem. But in the גמרא, Gemara, anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says that that's not realistic, that's not really going to solve the
problem anyway. It could also have been that we would have empowered
people rather than trying to send out a rabbinic inspector. Maybe we
should teach everybody, "Hey, people, before you buy תכלת, techelet, here's the
test that you have to run to know that you're buying kosher
תכלת." techelet. That at least makes more sense. You know, people are
going to spend an hour checking their הדסים hadasim and their לולבים
lulavim and so on before buying it, then we could tell people
what you have to do to make sure you're buying genuine תכלת.
techelet. And then the גמרא Gemara is going to say: okay, but
people will still make a mistake, they'll test it and then they'll
spill it back, and then we can't control what they're going to
do afterwards with the dye that they tested. So thinking that we're
talking about getting the people to inspect for themselves is at least,
I think, a better way of reading this גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so
now
the גמרא Gemara continues in the following way. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: "אי דמי משום טעמא וליכתבו אדיסקטי." i d'mi mishum
ta'ama u'lichtvu adiskatei. Let's write an announcement. So the גמרא Gemara says:
"אדיסקטי ליקו וליסמוך?" adiskatei liku u'lismoch? What, you think we're going to
just rely on an announcement? אמר רבא אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rava
amar Rav Yosef, Rava says, Rav Yosef says, "Why not? השתא, Hashta,
חמץ בפסח, chametz b'Pesach,
now we're on the עמוד ב. amud bet. So here you go,
very much מעניינא דיומא. me'inyana d'yoma. חמץ בפסח ויום הכיפורים דכרת סמכינן,"
chametz b'Pesach v'Yom HaKippurim d'kares samchinan,
when we make a leap year and we add an extra month,
right, which we do not know year by year, I mean I'm
not now going to get into the history of when the calendar
was totally fixed in terms of leap years, but there was obviously
a good period even after the חורבן churban when they were assessing
year by year whether to add a leap month. So when we
do that, how do we let people know? We send notices out
to, you know, to all of the diaspora. And we assume that
they're going to get those notices and that they'll keep יום כיפור
Yom Kippur on the right day and they'll keep פסח Pesach on
the right day. פסח, Pesach, you notice, is mentioned first because that's
the month that you have to find out right away that there's
a
leap year. הכא דאיתי בעלמא, Hacha de'isay be'alma, so here that
it's a simple עשה, aseh, לא כל שכן lo kol shekein certainly
we should be able to rely on these notices. Again, of course
there's a major difference, the holidays are celebrated communally and therefore when
people find out everybody's going to switch a practice. Here it is
about at an individual level, individuals testing and also you imagine if
I'm the person testing to see if I'm buying תכלת, techeilet, I'm
going to test a little, I see it is תכלת, techeilet, and
then like I'm done, it's like almost I'm sloppy, I don't care
what I do next, so I throw the rest back into the
vat. So here you're sort of leaving it at the negligence of
individuals as opposed to there where it's at a communal level. Nevertheless,
Rav is optimistic and he thinks that we can solve the problem
by sending out these notices. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא, ela,
so it can't be that our concern is if people are not
wearing the legitimate blue, so what's the concern? אלא אמר רבא, Ela
amar Rava, המיוותא אמר לי, Hamyuta amar li, I say the following
explanation, דאיתמר במערבא משמיה דרבי זירא כוותי de'itmar be'ma'arava mishmeih de'Rabbi Zeira
kevati
and it was said in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in the name
of רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira like me. What's the problem here? שמא
יקרע סדינו בתוך ג' ויתפרנו Shema yikara sadino betoch gimel ve'yitferenu that
התורה אמרה תעשה ולא מן העשוי. haTorah amrah ta'aseh velo min ha'asuy.
So again, it is a problem that you'll be wearing שעטנז shaatnez
without doing the מצות ציצית. mitzvah tzitzit. What is the problem? The
problem is is that the corner of your בגד beged will tear,
the corner which has the ציצית tzitzit suspended from it, and you
will
sew it back up and it'll and it'll tear within the three
lower lower טפחים tefachim and you are going to just like sew
this corner back onto the בגד beged and then you'll say, oh
good, so I fixed it. Like I took this corner that had
freestanding corner that had ציצית tzitzit holding flowing from it and I
sewed it back onto the בגד beged and now I've solved the
problem. But you didn't solve the problem, because you didn't put ציצית
tzitzit on your בגד, beged, you attached a piece of cloth and
then automatically the ציצית tzitzit appeared. That's תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta'aseh
velo min ha'asuy
and therefore you will invalidate your ציצית, tzitzit, you'll think it's good.
Normally, okay, what are we going to do about it? People will
do it and they won't be doing the מצוה, mitzvah, they'll think
they're doing the מצוה. mitzvah. But here it's worse because as soon
as you're not doing the מצוה, mitzvah, you're going to be עובר
over on the transgression of שעטנז. shaatnez. And therefore we can't have
you doing it. Now, why did he say that it'll tear
בתוך ג'? betoch gimel? So that's a little bit unclear. It sounds
like if it tore beyond ג' gimel and you sewed it up
that somehow that would be okay. Well, why wouldn't that also be
a תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta'aseh velo min ha'asuy problem? So תוספות
Tosafot says the following. One minute.
One minute.
Right, so תוספות Tosafot really reads the בתוך ג' betoch gimel a
little differently. And תוספות Tosafot reads the בתוך ג' betoch gimel meaning
is it still hanging on by it's not that the thing has
totally torn off. If the thing totally ripped off, maybe nobody would
sew it back on. The thing partially ripped off and it's still
connected by a little a little patch that is three that is
that is like three fingers wide. So if that patch is still
three fingers wide, it's still considered connected and you can sew it
back on. If that if that little if that little if that
little point of connection is less than שלשה טפחים shlosha tefachim wide,
then it's like it's totally disconnected and when you sew it back
on, it's תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta'aseh velo min ha'asuy. So that
is the problem. The problem is that you'll sew it back on,
it'll be תעשה, ta'aseh, it'll have torn off completely or mostly enough
that it's not considered connected. It's תעשה ולא מן העשוי, ta'aseh velo
min ha'asuy, you didn't really put the ציצית tzitzit on now and
you're going to be עובר שעטנז over shaatnez in your ציצית. tzitzit.
Now I will also remind you that this ties back to the
משנה Mishnah of the previous פרק perek because there was the position
of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili that said all three all
of the four corners are separate מצות mitzvot and and therefore even
if they don't are even if only three of them are sewn
on, you're not עובר over on שעטנז, shaatnez, right? Because because at
least it's a חפץ cheftz of ציצית tzitzit even if you're not
yet being יוצא yotzei the מצוה. mitzvah. Even according to רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili though, the problem might be this fourth corner.
This fourth corner is not considered part of the garment at all
and is not at all in the category of ציצית tzitzit and
maybe this fourth corner is the שעטנז shaatnez concern. Anyway, we don't
rule like רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, but that's one point.
Now, the other point Dov is asking and I mentioned before, yes,
there is a general concern you might always be concerned that somebody's
corners will tear and they'll sew it back on and they won't
do the מצוה. mitzvah. But at the end of the day, okay,
you didn't do the מצוה, mitzvah, you wore בגד beged without the
מצות ציצית. mitzvah tzitzit. Here the problem is that you're going to
be wearing שעטנז. shaatnez. So if you're going to be wearing שעטנז,
shaatnez, that we have to be extra concerned about that you're going
to do it wrong. It's just like a variation of the answer
of the blue. The same way the blue answer is, it's basically
when you're dealing with שעטנז, shaatnez, it's dangerous because if something goes
wrong, not only are you not doing the מצות ציצית, mitzvah tzitzit,
you're also transgressing שעטנז. shaatnez. So if the blue is wrong, you're
transgressing שעטנז. shaatnez. If the corner was sewn on after the fact,
you're transgressing שעטנז. shaatnez. And therefore it's a higher concern here. But
is it still עובר עשה over aseh if you wear a garment
with no ציצית? tzitzit? Yeah, you are being עובר over an עשה.
aseh. If you, oh, yes. That's a good point, right. So Dov,
you are correct, meaning, yes, the rabbis are willing to say we'd
rather you passively not do the מצות עשה mitzvas assei of ציצית
tzitzis and wear your linen garment with no ציצית tzitzis than passively
transgress, we'd, excuse me,
passively not do a מצוה, mitzvah, rather than the concern that you
might actually do an active transgression. Now remember, this is בית שמאי
Beis Shammai or the people of ירושלים Yerushalayim who followed this approach.
This is in general, if you would, this is a beautiful distillation
of the differences of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. Right, בית הלל, Beis Hillel, it's sort of like, you know,
it's sort of like the question about the way the גמרא Gemara
says it, a מדרש midrash says it is: which came first? שמים
וארץ shamayim va'aretz or ארץ? aretz? You know, בית שמאי Beis Shammai
says, you know, the שמים shamayim came first and בית הלל Beis
Hillel says the ארץ aretz came first. Which is like, which is
your primary concern? Are you first concerned that, oh my god, I
might transgress, you know, I don't want to violate God laws and
that has to override all things? So fine, if I passively am
not doing a מצוה, mitzvah, that's a great, that's better than opening
myself to the possibility of transgression. That's בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Whereas
בית הלל Beis Hillel says no, you emphasize, you know, the human
endeavor and the מצות mitzvos and the fulfillment and whatever and you
take proper safeguards, but ultimately, rather than, you know, it's like people
actually apropos of פסח, Pesach, you know, people there won't eat מצה
matzah the entire פסח Pesach other than the first night because they're
afraid it might be חמץ. chametz. So that's the בית שמאי Beis
Shammai approach. You're so anxious about the possible transgression you're limiting yourself
from the opportunity of certain מצות. mitzvos. So you're right, passively you
won't do the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית, tzitzis, but that's better for
him than opening yourself to the possibility of transgression. All right, I
see it's already pretty late. I see that Dov and Jedder are
still on, so we're going to go just for two more minutes
since we started late. So let's take a look. Oh, you know
what? I can't. I have to take my son to a סיום
בכורות. siyum bechoros. All right, so we will end here and we
will pick up. Dov, I'm sorry, I'm leaving you with a little
extra גמרא Gemara to do tomorrow, but we will, you can continue
from this point and it obviously just continues within the same theme.
All right, so חג כשר ושמח chag kasher v'sameach to everybody and
be well. What? סיום
בכורות?
siyum bechoros?